<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the worship of God towards the holy table or altar</title>
            <author>Penton, Stephen, 1639-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31106</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11779372</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11779372</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1491:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the worship of God towards the holy table or altar</title>
                  <author>Penton, Stephen, 1639-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 105 [i.e. 120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. to be sold by James Good ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Penton.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the worship of God towards the altar.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Posture in worship.</term>
               <term>Altars.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48970:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48970:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the WORSHIP of GOD Towards the Holy Table OR ALTAR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J.G.</hi> to be ſold by <hi>James Good,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Oxon:</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:48970:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48970:2"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe, ſhewing, That the Adoration or Worſhip of God in his Houſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the H. Table or Altar, is neither Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Superſtition, or Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip: but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary agreeable to the Scriptures, and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Practice of the Saints in all Ages.</head>
            <p>THey that go about to evince a Truth,
<note place="margin">To remove pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice.</note> and to demonſtrate unto the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſuch as have ſtrongly oppoſed it before as an error, will find it a hard task, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impoſſible, unleſs he can firſt perſwade them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs themſelves of one Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48970:3"/>which is uſually deeply rooted in the hearts of ſuch as are already prejudiced with an ill opinion of this Doctrine to be evinced: That is, becauſe they would not be thought to be ſo Impotent in Judgment, as ſo long to have believed and maintained an Error; or out of a ſelf-conceit, and opinion of their own infallibility, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they have once held, muſt needs be Truth, reſolve abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unmovedly to defend it; never conſidering the connexion between the premiſſes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of their Adverſaries Arguments: or rather, what agreement the whole Argument hath with the concluſion which they have formerly hardened: themſelves to defend unalterab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: therefore I intreat the Reader, that he will for the time, at leaſt make himſelf a Third Perſon, and degage himſelf from both Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, as if he were Ignorant of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48970:3"/>both, that ſo he may be a free and impartial Judge, not weighing how my Arguments comply with his private perſwaſion, but what neceſſary connexion there is between my Arguments and the Cauſe or Concluſion I have undertaken to prove;
<note place="margin">The Order.</note> in handling whereof I will obſerve this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I will explain the Queſtion and ſtate it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I will prove it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>I will clear it from all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections and Aſperſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But firſt,
<note place="margin">Obj. <hi>from the word Altar.</hi>
               </note> I will remove one Objection againſt the word [Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar] What have we to do with Altars? If Altars, we muſt have Prieſts, and Sacrifices too, for theſe are Correlates, and ſo we ſhall have Judaiſm up again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I grant the Antecedent,
<note place="margin">Reſp. It doth not infer Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm.</note> but deny the Conſequent. An Altar, a Prieſthood, a Sacrifice, I grant; that this will infer Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm, I deny. For thoſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48970:4"/>Prieſts, and Sacrifices, were but Typical ſhadows of the true ones; and therefore not ſo properly called, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the true ones; otherwiſe Chriſts offering himſelf was not a true and Real Sacrifice, nor he a true and Real Prieſt, nor his Croſs a true and real Altar: but this to be falſe is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent by Scripture, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. The Apoſtle makes a diſtinction of a double Prieſthood, one Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical, the other Real; that after the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> this after the Order of <hi>Melchiſedeck:</hi> that to be aboliſhed, this to remain for ever: that had no perfection, this had: of this Order was our Saviour a Prieſt, ſo called for this very reaſon, becauſe he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf a Sacrifice for Sin; ſo <hi>Corinth.</hi> the 9th. and 10th. he plainly diſparageth the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Law, and makes our Saviours the only true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Sacrifice. Therefore I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48970:4"/>the Argument thus, we have an Altar, a Sacrifice and Prieſthood; <hi>Ergo,</hi> we aboliſh the Jewiſh Ceremonies, for they were not ſuch properly, but ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pically; theſe are ſo truly, as being the ſubſtance of thoſe Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows.
<note place="margin">Communion Service.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, our Church, in the Prayer immediatlye before the Conſecration, calls our Saviours ſuffering on the Croſs, a full,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.7.</note> perfect and ſufficient Sacrifice. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Chriſt our Paſſover is Sacrificed,</hi> &amp;c. For he indeed is the true Paſchal Lamb, of which the other was but the Type; therefore the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo calleth that Feaſt ſtill, and ever did, <hi>Feſtum Paſchatis,</hi> and not the Feaſt of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.
<note place="margin">Pet. 2.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Alms, and Prayers, and Praiſes are Sacrifices, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.16. Prayers, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 141.2. They are called the Calves of our Lips. And what more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48970:5"/>than the Sacrifice of Praiſe? Theſe are called Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sacrifices, in which reſpect we are called an Holy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. This I ſpeak to vindicate the word, that it might not ſeem ſo odious, which the Holy-Ghoſt himſelf ſtill uſeth in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> I grant that there are Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sacrifices and Prieſts, and Altars, <hi>viz.</hi> the Altars of Hearts, but what is all this to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table? Or though we allow Chriſt to be a Prieſt, and his offering himſelf, a true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and the Croſs a true Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, yet why ſhould the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table, the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and the Miniſters of the Goſpel be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by theſe Names?</p>
            <p>By what I have before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> it appears that theſe words do not neceſſarily infer Judaiſm, but the contrary, and ſo that part of the objection is ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48970:5"/>To the other <hi>Quaeri</hi> (what reaſon we have to call the Holy Table an Altar, Miniſters Prieſts,
<note place="margin">Sacraments fitly called a Sacifice.</note> the Sacrament a Sacrifice) I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, they are ſo, and ſo called in Scripture: and Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and all Churches to this time, until ſome Muſhroom No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Puritans ſprang up, that out of Ignorance and blind Zeal would have ſuppreſſed them. That they are ſo I prove thus.</p>
            <p>If the Sacrifices of the Law and Paſchal Lamb were ſuch, and ſo called by reaſon of the reference they had to the true Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, not yet exhibited, then may the Sacramental Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of this Sacrifice alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy exhibited, be much more fitly ſo called. The force of this Argument ſtands thus: If the Shadow may be called by the name of the Antitype, then much more may the true, real
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48970:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and lively Commemoration of the thing it ſelf, already in act. Now Sacrifices were but ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe they were Shadows; the Sacrament is a true real, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, and lively Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of the Sacrifice it ſelf, and that by vertue of Chriſt's own words, <hi>Do this, as oft as you do it in remembrance of me.</hi> Do this, do what? <hi>This ye have ſeen me do.</hi> What's that? He took Bread, gave Thanks, brake it, ſaid, <hi>this is my Body, Take, Eat:</hi> He took Wine, poured it out, ſaid, <hi>drink ye all of this, this is my Blood which is ſhed for many, for the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins, &amp;c.</hi> Mark it, what was the breaking of his Body in the Bread, the pouring out of his Blood in the Wine, was it not a Sacrifice? ſure it was, for it was for the Remiſſion of Sins. Now no Remiſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Blood, no Blood without a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48970:6"/>Sacrifice, ſo the Apoſtle argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> Again, he ſaith not which ſhall be, but which is broken and poured out, as already done, when as yet he was not Crucified: which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues that this Sacrament was inſtituted in memory of Chriſt's Sacrifice already done, though inſtituted before it was done. Again, do this in remembrance of me, Sacrificed for you, of me broken for you, of my Blood poured out for you, that is, of my Sacrifice for your ſins. For, for what elſe could our Saviour be remembred, or what elſe do the Elements repreſent or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate but that Sacrifice?</p>
            <p>Thus then you ſee that as the old Jewiſh Sacrifices were Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical Sacrifices, ſo the Chriſtian Sacrament, is a memorative Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: And that one and the ſame thing might be both a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and a Sacrifice, none
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48970:7"/>will deny that conſiders the Paſchal Lamb was both: Yet that was but a Typical Sacrifice, and a Typical Sacrament; this both a true Sacrifice and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For although that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt on the Croſs, was performed once for all, yet the Commemoration of it was to be often iterated in the Church, till Chriſt's ſecond coming.</p>
            <p>Again, why ſhould we not as well call it a Sacrifice in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt's, which it ſignifies, as a Sacrament in token of his which it Seals, or in token of a Covenant which it ratifies. The Scripture, I am ſure, no where calleth it by the name of Sacrament,
<note place="margin">Sacrament, the word not found in the Bible.</note> for there is no ſuch word in the <hi>Bible.</hi> And therefore they that will have a Proof out of the Scripture for every thing they ſay,
<note place="margin">'Tis a Seal to the Covenant, and therefore a Sacrifice.</note> and give no reſpect to the Cuſtom and Language of the Church, muſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48970:7"/>deſiſt by their own principles from the uſe of this word; for they can have no Authority for it, but the conſtant and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous tradition of the Church.</p>
            <p>Moreover, God never made Covenant with man, but with Sacrifice. For a Covenant ſince the fall, was always made for the redintegration of our peace with God, violated by ſin: Now there was no peace, that is, no Covenant renewed, where there was no firſt remiſſion of ſin paſt; and no remiſſion of ſin without ſatisfaction of Juſtice; no ſatisfaction without the blood of a Sacrifice, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. For that is the ground of our Covenant with God, and therefore whereſoever it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, that Sacrifice is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all commemorated; in vertue whereof it was at firſt made, and ever ſince renewed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48970:8"/>Beſides, as in Sacrifices, God in token of Covenant and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, with man, did as it were eat with him, and Feaſt him at his own Table (eating and drinking, having been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways eſteemed tokens of Peace and Friendſhip) (For the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices were firſt preſented, and given up unto God, conſecrated unto him in Recognition of his Lordſhip over all Creatures, then afterwards Slaughtered and Offered, part whereof was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, the other part was for the Sacrifice to Feaſt withal in token of Reconciliation with God) ſo alſo is the Sacrament a Foederal Rite of our Addreſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to renew a Covenant. The Bread and Wine are firſt Conſecrated and made the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt, that is, a memorial of that Sacrifice which is the ground of our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and then are given as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48970:8"/>meat from Gods Table, to be a Sacrament ſealing unto us his Reconciliation, in vertue of his Sons Sacrifice there commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. You ſee then, that this Sacrament is, how it is, and why it is a Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Now if it be truly a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<note place="margin">Holy Table may fitly be called an Altar.</note> the Holy Table may fitly be called an Altar: For as the Croſs was the Altar of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Sacrifice corporally of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; ſo is the Table the Altar of his Sacrifice myſtically of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Supper. And as a Croſs did ſuit to his Body, ſo a Table to the Bread. As he did not inſtitute any Carnal Body and Blood to be the memory of his Sacrifice, but Bread and Wine; ſo he did not inſtitute a Croſs for an Altar, but that which was proportionable to the ſigns which he inſtituted. As in the Old Law, it was not neceſſary that the Type ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48970:9"/>in every thing be ſo Analogal, as to have a man Crucified for a Sacrifice, and a Croſs for an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, to repreſent the Sacrifice of Chriſt; but a Beaſt for the one, and a Table for the other: ſo neither is it neceſſary in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> the ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Body of a Man ſhould be the ſign of Chriſt's Sacrifice, or a Croſs of an Altar for the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof. And this I have the more fully enlarged, to anſwer thoſe, who will perchance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our Saviours Croſs to have been an Altar, but not our Tables.</p>
            <p>Furthermore,
<note place="margin">Table and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly uſed.</note> what great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial difference is there between an Altar and a Table, that we are ſo ſcrupelous? were not the Altars of the Old Law Tables? elſe what means the promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſe of theſe words,
<note place="margin">Mal. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Ye of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer polluted Bread upon mine Altar</hi> (mark it) and ye ſay,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48970:9"/>
               <hi>wherein have we polluted thee?</hi> The anſwer of God by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, is in that ye ſay the Table of the Lord is contemptible. That which in the beginning of the Verſe is called an Altar, in the end is called a Table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The word doth not infer Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note> What's this but by little and little to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in Popery un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand, when we begin to uſe their Language? for ſo Popery came in, and got head at firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> No ſuch matter, Let the Papiſt take away their Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation or Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preſence, and we ſhall not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from them in the uſe of this word; for it is not theirs, but the Speech of the Scripture and the Primitive Church. The Papiſt may with as good reaſon ſay, that the Table is tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated into a Croſs, as the Bread into the Body. For if our Saviour by thoſe words
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48970:10"/>
               <hi>(This is my Body)</hi> did mean to exhibit ſubſtantially that once offered Sacrifice, even that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body Crucified, every time the Euchariſt ſhould be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and ſo to make it a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice for the Quick and Dead, then it is neceſſary that he ſhould mean alſo to turn the Table into the Croſs. For that was the real Altar of his real Sacrifice. And therefore if they will have the true Body and Blood, litterally underſtood to be then Crucified and Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: I ſee not how they can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the inferring of a true Croſs, whereinto the Table muſt be likewiſe turned. For a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was not the Altar of Chriſt's Bodily Sacrifice, but a Croſs. I know no reaſon why I ſhould imagine the ſame Indentical, Numerical, real bodily Sacrifice, and not the ſame Indentical, Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical real Altar. The ſame
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48970:10"/>Numerical Sacrifice (ſay they) was offered on the Croſs; nay, his Cruſifying was his Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; but no Crucifying but on a Croſs: therefore if his Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Sacrificing be there, his Numerical Cruſifying is alſo there; if his Numerical Cruſify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then his Numerical Croſs. Theſe things do neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult one from another, and all joyntly ſhew the abſurdity of the Popiſh Error.</p>
            <p>But now, becauſe they mix falſhood with truth, ſhall we relinquiſh the truth? Becauſe they make the Sacrament a real Corporal Sacrifice, ſhall not we hold it to be a commemorative one, as Chriſt teacheth us? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſay in the Sacrament Chriſt is Bodily, ſhall we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deny that he is there real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? So neither muſt we deny the Table to be an Altar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hold Tranſubſtantion and ſay Maſs at it. For this is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48970:11"/>to refuſe Gold becauſe of Droſs, Wheat becauſe of Tares, Corn becauſe of Chaff, which is mere folly.</p>
            <p>But come we now to ſhew the uſe of theſe words out of Scripture.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The uſe of the word Altar in Scripture.</hi> Hebr. 13.10.</note> The Apoſtle ſaith expreſly we have an Altar, we under the Goſpel; for he makes an Antitheſis or Oppoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the legal Altars and this, in that thoſe who Miniſter at the Tabernacle, have not right to eat of things offered upon this. And why ſo? Becauſe while they retain the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical obſervances, now aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they argue Chriſt the true Sacrifice not to be exhibited, and therefore have no right to eat of the Sacrifices of our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, which commemorate Chriſt already Sacrificed; or elſe I know no reaſon but the Jews ſhould have as much intereſt in Chriſt as the Gentiles, and be as much partakers of this Altar,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48970:11"/>would they believe in him as we do. But to wait at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, that is, to obſerve le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Rites, cannot conſiſt with our eating of Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, or participating of our Altar, becauſe the one makes Chriſt not come, the other commemorates him already come. That this is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle is evident, becauſe in the following verſes, he compares the Type with the Antitype, and ſhews how Chriſt did anſwer and fulfil all the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Sacrifices, and inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appoint his own, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently aboliſh the former, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Miniſtery of the Jewiſh Prieſts, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle makes the reaſon of this Speech, <hi>We have an Altar, whereof they have not right to eat, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides,
<note place="margin">And that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-Table.</note> what other thing can be meant hereby, but the Communion-Table? For it is an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48970:12"/>Altar from which ſome thing is eaten that was Sacrificed; for nothing was eaten on the Altar but what was offered to God in Sacrifice. But what other Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar can that be but the Holy-Table, whereat we eat the Lords Supper, and commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate his Sacrifice? You ſee by this then that the Holy-Table was thus called even by Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> If you ſay, he called it ſo improperly, and Anologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in reference to the Jewiſh Altars, This I have diſproved, in ſhewing that thoſe were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improperly termed Altars and Sacrifices in reference to ours, whereof they were but Types.</p>
            <p>Now having proved an Altar, by your own conſequence we muſt have a Sacrifice too, and a Prieſthood, for theſe you ſay infer one another as Correlates. But I will not be beholden to you to make this my Argument,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48970:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>but will prove out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The word Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to our Sacrament.</hi> Matt. 1.10.</note> the word Sacrifice to be applied to our Sacrament.</p>
            <p>God by his Prophet foretels the Jews, that whereas they had polluted his Altars, he had alſo rejected them and their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and would appoint himſelf a new People, and new Sacrifice. In every place (that is not in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> only, and in one place) Incenſe ſhall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto his Name, and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium Purum,</hi> a pure Sacrifice or Offering, for ſo the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> Now what other Incenſe have we but Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? What other Sacrifice but the Lords Supper? Which he calls a pure Sacrifice or Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which God hath appointed to commemorate the Death and Sacrifice of his Son, inſtead of the Jewiſh Sacrifice which only Typified it.</p>
            <p>This is the Interpretation of the moſt, and moſt Antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48970:13"/>For among all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Fathers both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> there is nothing more frequent than the uſe of theſe words Sacrifice, Prieſts, Altar, when they ſpeak of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Holy-Table, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel. No man can deny this, that hath but caſt his Eyes upon their Writings, who are every where full of theſe expreſſions. He that ſhall vilifie their Authority in this, let him give me better for the contrary, or I ſhall conclude him ignorant and impudent.</p>
            <p>Add the conſtant uſe of theſe words in the Church even to this day, both of the Eaſtern Church of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who have no Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches beſides the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Reformed Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran Churches and our own, wherein theſe words were never out of uſe; but that of late
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48970:13"/>ſome Novelliſts who love to antiquate all things that are Antient, that their own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern intentions might be more in credit, have laboured to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs men with an ill opinion of them, by telling them they were Popiſh names, a ſimple reaſon. For if theſe names be therefore naught becauſe the Papiſts uſe them, then, ſeeing <hi>a quatenus ad de omnis valet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentia</hi> (as Logitians ſpeak) then all other names which the Papiſts uſe are naught, and we muſt not call the Lords Supper a Sacrament becauſe of them, nor Chriſten onr Children, <hi>John, Thomas, Robert,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe they do ſo. Muſt we run from the Papiſts in every thing, becauſe they err in many things? This is to run from Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed how the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is a Commemorative Sacrifice,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48970:14"/>and the Holy Table an Altar' that it is ſo called in Scriptures, Fathers, and all Churches. Now why are the Miniſters of the Goſpel called Prieſts?</p>
            <p>The word Prieſt (if we look to the Notation and Original of it) is the only proper word for the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prieſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name of the Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi> 1 Pet. 5.1.</note> for it is nothing but the contraction or corruption of the word Presbyter, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies an Elder. So that Prieſt and Elder is all one, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we read the word Elder, we may as well read it Prieſt; as the Elders I exhort, that is, the Prieſts I exhort who am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Prieſt. Now Chriſt would have the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel called Prieſts or Elders, not in reſpect of their Age, but in regard of their Function and Preheminence over the People, as being their Teachers and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors, in which reſpect alſo the People, though for their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48970:14"/>Age they may be Elder than the Prieſt; yet in regard of their ſubordination to him, are called Younger.</p>
            <p>Again,
<note place="margin">Miniſters of the proper name, of the Prieſts of the Law.</note> as the word Prieſt is the term proper to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel; ſo is the word Miniſter proper to thoſe whom we call Prieſts of the Law. For the word in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> which the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were pleaſed to render Prieſt (not obſerving this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which I have told you) doth not indeed ſignify any ſuch thing, though that alſo be a word of Dignity; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we tranſlate Prieſt, ſignifies one that Miniſters about Holy things, and therefore the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and the <hi>Latin ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos</hi> do more truly expreſs the meaning of that word, than our Engliſh Prieſt; for we ſhould rather render it a Holy Miniſter, or a Miniſter about Holy Things; or one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48970:15"/>that attends about holy ſervice;)
<note place="margin">Neh. 10.36. Eſay 61.6. Jer. 33.21.</note> and therefore Scripture it ſelf gives this interpretation of their names in very many places. For though there were diverſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in the Jewiſh Hierarchy, as the High-Prieſt, the Prieſts, the Levites, Nethemims, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Singers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet were they all Miniſters about Holy Things, though ſome in a higher, others in a lower rank. For the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites Miniſtred immediately to the Prieſts, the Prieſts to the High Prieſt, and he immediatly to God: as in our Church, the Deacon (whoſe name ſignifies a Miniſter) Miniſters to the Prieſt, and the Prieſt immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God. Therefore Prieſt, Levite,
<note place="margin">Ezr. 7.24.</note> Nethemims, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are all ſum'd up in this name of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſee <hi>Joel.</hi> 1.9. and 13. where they are all called Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Altar. So <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48970:15"/>Thus you ſee what the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> word ſignifies, which we turn Prieſt, and what the <hi>Greek</hi> word Prieſt ſignifies, which we would not have the Clergy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by, and yet it is the very word given them by the Holy Ghoſt, in the <hi>New-Teſtament, viz.</hi> Elders.</p>
            <p>Now I pray,
<note place="margin">The Dignity of the Prieſts.</note> if they who waited on the Altar, were called Miniſters of God, or of the Sanctuary, or of the Holy Things, why may not we of the Goſpel be ſo called, that is, Prieſts, for that the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ment when they tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Hebrew Cohen?</hi> which word likewiſe ſignifies a Prince, to intimate the great Dignity of that Function which conſiſted in Miniſtring unto God about Holy Things. And of no leſs Dignity is the word Prieſt or Elder. And therefore theſe terms were premiſcuouſly given to the Jewiſh Clergy, and an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48970:16"/>Elder with them ſometimes ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Prince. So the Elders of the People, of the City, of the Congregation, fignifies Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Governours.</p>
            <p>To be God's Miniſters is to be the Peoples Elders;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>We are the Miniſters of God, not men.</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 4. 1 Cor. 4. 1. 2 Cor. 3. 6. Rom. 13. 6.</note> for we are not the Miniſters of men, but of God, and ſo we are ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Miniſters of Chriſt, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Spirit, God and Chriſt ſet us on work, he ſends us forth, to him we Miniſter, though for you. When we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Holy Word, the Sacraments, we are not therein your Miniſters, but his Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers or Stewards: For we do it, not at your appointment or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or by your Authority, but by Gods, from whom we have our Calling and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. As the King is not his Subjects Miniſter, though he doth adminiſter Juſtice to them, and therefore he is called Gods Miniſter. Angels likewiſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48970:16"/>Spirits to God, even then when they are ſent out for the good of them, who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.21: 104.4.</note> For though the material Object of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, or that whereabout their Miniſtery is converſant, be men, yet the formal Object, or he in reference to whom this Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is executed, is God. Hence ye Prieſts, ye Miniſters of his that do his pleaſure; and he maketh his Miniſters a flame; and <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſaith of them thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſands Miniſtred unto them.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee then whoſe Miniſters we are, Gods,
<note place="margin">Dan. 1.10.</note> not mens. Secondly, What a Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity this is, it is no leſs than what is attributed to Kings and Angels. You ſee likewiſe that what the Interpreters tranſlated Prieſts, ſignifies that which you call us, Miniſters, and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of their Office, Miniſtring or Miniſtration. As alſo that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48970:17"/>the word Elder,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.23.</note> that the Holy Ghoſt calls us by, is all one with the word Prieſt. And therefore if you be ſo much againſt the Jewiſh terms, you ſhould rather call us Prieſts than Miniſters: but indeed we are both, and the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uſeth both words promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly, as well in the <hi>Old</hi> as the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> For we are Elders in reſpect of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Miniſters in reſpect of God, and we Miniſter to God about Holy Things; unleſs you will ſay that our Goſpel is not ſo Holy as their Law, our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as their Expounding, our Prayers, and Service, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, wherein is the Body and Blood of our Saviour, are not as Holy as their Incenſe, Oblation and Sacrifice; for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe things are our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters converſant.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the main Queſtion, concerning Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48970:17"/>or Worſhip of God before, or towards the Altar, in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs into his houſe, or at any other time when we ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach thereunto. Where firſt, I will ſhew you what is meant by Adoration or Worſhip, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, what is meant by the Houſe of God,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Worſhip,
<note place="margin">What is meant by Worſhip.</note> I do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand here in the Latitude of the word, the whole Act of Religion, the whole Duty of Man, which ſometimes is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſo called, the Worſhip of God, the Fear of God, nor yet only or primarily the inward Reverence and Devotion of the heart, but in ſpecial, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward expreſſion of Reverence and Humility in the poſture or geſture of the Body, not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but implying the inward worſhiping of the mind. In this ſenſe the word is often ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Holy Scripture, as in the ſecond Commandment,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48970:18"/>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24: 26.48.5. Rev. 19.10.</note> nor Worſhip them.</hi> So Saint <hi>John</hi> fell at the Angels feet to Worſhip him: but the Angel refuſeth it, and biddeth him worſhip God, that is, give the outward Worſhip that he was ready to do to him, to God, to whom alone it was due. For had not the outward Worſhip been an Act of Religion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Saint <hi>John</hi>'s intention, and inward Reverence, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel needed not to have refuſed it; for outward Worſhip if it be only Civil, is ſuch as one man may give to another, a Subject to his Prince, much more to an Angel.</p>
            <p>You ſee then the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the name of Worſhip, doth oftentimes mean in ſpecial the outward Adoration of the Body in viſible geſtures; and ſo do I here. Now this Act of outward Worſhip, I make a part of Religion, which that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48970:18"/>you may the better conceive, I will tell you the Nature and Parts thereof: For it is not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally believed that outward Worſhip is due unto God, and conſequently that it is part of Religion.</p>
            <p>Religion,
<note place="margin">Religion, the Nature and Parts.</note> which is derived from a word that ſignifies bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Implies three things: 1. An Act of Duty. 2. The Object of that Act, God. 3. The Bond or Tye impoſed upon us for the performance of ſuch a Duty to ſuch an Object.</p>
            <p>The Object of Religion is God, moſt Infinite, moſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, moſt Excellent and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and therefore our Act of Duty, in reference to ſuch an Object, ought to have three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties:
<note n="3" place="margin">Properties of it.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be an univerſal Act, or Act of the whole Man,
<note n="1" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal of Soul and Body.</note> Soul and Body, of all the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul, and of all the Members of the Body. All are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48970:19"/>to concur in this Act of Duty to God, and that for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe God is to be worſhipped by us as men; now, Men we are not without our Bodies; nor our Actions, the Actions of Men without our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>Actiones ſunt ſuppoſitorum,</hi> ſay the Schools, Chriſt had not been true Man without a Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Our Bodies as well as our Souls are Liable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and puniſhments, and therefore with them muſt God be worſhipped, if we expect they ſhould be Bleſſed; and with them we ſhould be Damn'd, if we deny God's Worſhip by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bond of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> The common Bond which ties us to this Act of Duty to this Object, requireth outward Worſhip of the Body, which Bond is the right which God hath to require this Duty of us, which is grounded upon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48970:19"/>his abſolute Dominion and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty, and that is founded on his Communication of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or Being unto us. He made both Body and Soul, and wherefore, but that both ſhould ſerve him? Again,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.20.</note> Again, his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual preſervation of both, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles him to the Service of both; Laſtly, his Redeeming of both, multiplies his claim of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Worſhip of both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 12.30.</note> Our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands this univerſal Act, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy mind, with all thy Soul, and with all thy Strength. i. e.</hi> with thy Body alſo, for there is ſtrength in that. Thus you ſee the Act of Religion muſt be an univerſal Act, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently outward Worſhip and Reverence is comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Act of Religion muſt be the moſt excellent,
<note n="2" place="margin">Intenſe.</note> moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48970:20"/>and perfect we can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, ſo that all other Actions muſt be hereunto ſubordinate; For he is moſt excellent and perfect, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves our beſt performances. So that as he is to be worſhiped with all of man, ſo with the intenſeſt Devotion, Zeal and Reverence of that All: The whole Activity of all muſt be taken up in this Act of Duty or Service.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note n="3" place="margin">Conſtant.</note> It muſt be a conſtant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, uninterrupted Act, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Gods Right and Dominion over us is conſtant and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. Not that we muſt always be converſant in every part of Divine Worſhip, always bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Body, always Praying, or praiſing with the Tongue, always hearing, always medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating of him in our hearts, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways at Church: But ſo as all our Actions, whither we eat, or drink, ſleep or wake, talk, walk,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48970:20"/>work or play, ſhould be to his Glory, all ſhould tend to him as to the Center, all ordered and governed by his Will, all ſhould be ſubordinated unto Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that always.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewn what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is, and that outward Worſhip is a part of it. Now I come to a more preciſe and ſpecial conſideration of outward Worſhip in it ſelf;
<note place="margin">What outward Worſhip is.</note> And this is nothing elſe but an expreſſing and teſtifying of the mind. For though I do conſider theſe Acts of outward and inward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the explication of them diſtinctly, yet I deny them to be ſeparated in the true uſe and practiſe: For the whole Act of Adoration, concretely taken, doth imply both;
<note place="margin">The defination.</note> whence it is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a yielding of Honour to the thing worſhipped, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition of its Dignity and Excellency, and by a religious ſubmiſſion of Body and Soul, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48970:21"/>by inward motion of the Will, and outward teſtimonies and expreſſions of the Body.</p>
            <p>Where note,
<note place="margin">The parts.</note> three Acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to the compleat Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip. 1. The Act of the Underſtanding,
<note n="1" place="margin">Eſtimation.</note> whereby we apprehend the excellency of the thing we Worſhip: For the Will cannot incline it ſelf with a reverential eſteem towards that which the Underſtanding doth not firſt conceive excellent, and worthy ſuch reverence. 2. The Act of the Will,
<note n="2" place="margin">Affection.</note> which, upon the preceeding Act of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, apprehending the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject excellent, doth inwardly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline it ſelf thereto, in its af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Love and Reverence. 3.
<note n="3" place="margin">Outward expreſſiion.</note> The Act of the Body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we do by ſome outward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of reſpect and honour ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the excellency thereof, which we conceive in our minds, and reverence in our hearts, by a ſubmiſſion of our wills thereto.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48970:21"/>Both which inward Acts are not only teſtified by the outward, but intended, encreaſed, and conſummated thereby.</p>
            <p>All theſe three Acts muſt concur in one Worſhip or Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; For if the firſt be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we ſhall Worſhip with the <hi>Athenians,</hi> an unknown God. If the ſecond, our Worſhip will be Hypocritical. If the third, it will be maimed and imperfect. Now this third and laſt Act of bodily Worſhip, which is the thing in Queſtion, being the Effect of the two former Acts, and the witneſs of them, is by a <hi>Synechdoche</hi> more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called Adoration.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adoration and its kinds.</hi> Nudatio.</note> Of which there are reckoned up four ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or ſorts: 1. <hi>Nudatio Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> uncovering the head.
<note place="margin">Geniculatio.</note> 2. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculatio,</hi> bowing of the knee. 3. <hi>Incurvatio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Incurvatio.</note> bowing of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. 4. <hi>Proſtratio,</hi> Proſtration,
<note place="margin">Proſtratio.</note> or falling down. The firſt of theſe is proper only to the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48970:22"/>part of the World, where the faſhion is to teſtify our Worſhip to any body by unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the head, (I ſpeak of men). In the Eaſtern Countrys they never were wont to bare their heads, nor is it the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there to this day: But the other three have been always uſed in the Service of God, by Jews, Greeks, Chriſtians, and all Nations of the World.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Very frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned in Scripture.</hi> Gen. 24. 26. Exo. 4.32. <hi>and</hi> 2.27. <hi>and</hi> 34.8. 2 Cor. 7.8. <hi>and</hi> 29.29. Eſay 44.47. Dan. 3.6. Job 1.20. Matt. 2.11. <hi>and</hi> 20.26.</note> you ſeldom read of Worſhipping in Holy Scripture, but there is ſome Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture expreſſed with it, as bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head, falling down, bowing to the ground. The Jews in diriſion of our Saviour, could not mock a Worſhip, without expreſſing it by bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.9. Did not Saint <hi>Paul</hi> Worſhip, when he bowed his knees to the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt? Eph.</hi> 3.14. And what is our Saviours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward now he ſits at the Right
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48970:22"/>Hand of his Father, which the Holy Scripture expreſſeth by bowing the knee at his Name, is it not worſhipping him? that you may ſee how little, or no Worſhip, was uſed by the Saints of God in the <hi>Old</hi> or <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> without external Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Bowing, <hi>Abrahams</hi> Servant, the <hi>Iſraelites, Jacob</hi> their Father, <hi>Moſes, Job, David,</hi> Come let us Worſhip, and fall down and kneel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as if no worſhipping without theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations). And the wiſe men, and the Leaper, and <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> all theſe could not worſhip without bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or kneeling, or ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily teſtification of their inward Reverence, Submiſſion, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the meaning of the word Worſhip or Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the neceſſity of it, being an Act of Religion, and the commendation of it, in that it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48970:23"/>is the continual practiſe of God's Saints recorded in Scripture.</p>
            <p>Come we now to conſider,
<note n="2" place="margin">Of the houſe of God.</note> what is meant by the houſe of God, by which I mean the Chriſtian Oratories and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, places devoted and ſet apart for the ſolemn and publick Worſhip of Almighty God. And firſt, I will ſhew the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſuch places, and then the Holineſs of them, which two things, many will hardly believe.</p>
            <p>The neceſſity I prove,
<note n="1" place="margin">The neceſſity of Churches proved.</note> becauſe it is a principle in Nature; the very Common-Law of Nature did ever ſuggeſt unto men, that God was to have a place ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peculiar manner to his Worſhip. This I will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate firſt by reaſon, and then confirm it by example.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note n="1" place="margin">By reaſon.</note> I ſuppoſe none will deny, but that it is a main Principle in Nature, 1. That there is a God. 2. That he is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48970:23"/>3. That there muſt be ſome time ſet apart for his Worſhip. Now if we hold (as who doth not?) that it is part of the Moral Law, that God muſt have a diſtinct and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar time conſecrated and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for his Worſhip, which is the Effect of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; it will then alſo follow, by the ſame Law of Nature, that he muſt have a place Sanctified unto him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fourth Commandment doth (though not directly,) yet by neceſſary conſequence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force and enjoyn a Holy-Place, as well as a Holy-day, or time: For time, and place are both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like neceſſary Circumſtances of Divine Worſhip: And he can no more be worſhipped with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a place, than without a time; And therefore if the time ought to be conſecrate and ſolemn, ſo muſt the place likewiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48970:24"/>2. <note n="2" place="margin">
                  <hi>By exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the</hi> Old Teſtament.</note> This may be confirmed from the example of God's Saints, approved by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the beginning. Before ever there was a Tabernacle or Temple made by God's ſpecial appointment,
<note place="margin">Gen. 8.20. Gen. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Noah</hi> built an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar ſo ſoon as he came out of the Ark, and there called upon God with Sacrifice. <hi>Abraham</hi> builds an Altar (that is a ſpecial place to invocate at) in the place where God appeared to him:
<note place="margin">c. 13.4.</note> and wherever he came in his Journeys, he ſtill erected an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or place of Worſhip; and when ever he came into any of toſe places afterwards, there he ſtill worſhipped God at the place where he had formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated. The ſame I might ſhew of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who ſtill erected Altars in the place where they Pitched their Tents, and that without any ſpecial ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God. <hi>Jacob</hi> vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a place for Divine Worſhip,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48970:24"/>by the name of Gods houſe, where he would pay Tithes of all that God ſhould give him. Yea <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 20.22.</note> before the Ark and that glorious Tabernacle were made, pitched a Tabernacle for the ſame purpoſe, without the Camp, whither every one that ſought the Lord, was to go;
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.7.</note> which he called the Tabernacle of the Congregation, or rather of Meeting, becauſe God meets with man there, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee men naturally were wont to accommodate the Worſhip of God from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, with conſecrate places, as well as times: Yea, before the Law was given of any ſet or preciſe time; for that was not until the Decalogue was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by <hi>Moſes:</hi> Which argues, that Nature likewiſe had taught them that the work was honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dignified by the peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arneſs of the place appointed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48970:25"/>for it: And that ſuch a place beſt beſeemed the Worſhip of God, the moſt peculiar and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable Act.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe apparent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of the</hi> New Teſtament.</note> that Chriſtians had their peculiar Oratories, and ſet places for their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and Meeting to celebrate Gods Worſhip:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.8.</note> For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives Rules of behaviour how to carry our ſelves in ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Let the Women keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the Church:</hi> which that he underſtands not of the Company only gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but of the place likewiſe where they were met; it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe he puts a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between this and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>If they will learn any thing, let them ask their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands at home; for 'tis not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a Woman to ſpeak in the Church.</hi> where you ſee, he puts a plain difference between their own Houſes, and the places of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48970:25"/>publick meeting for God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which he could not do, if there had been no ſuch places. So likewiſe,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>have ye not houſes to eat and to drink in, or diſpiſe ye the Church of God?</hi> He chides them for their Irreverent receiving of the Lord's Supper, and puts a difference between their houſes, and the places where they met for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Thus much to evince the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Houſes and Oratories for God's publick Service.
<note place="margin">The Sanctity of Churches.</note> Come we now to prove the Sanctity and Holineſs of them, where we will conſider, 1. What it is. 2. Where it is. 3. How long it is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a double Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, one Poſitive, the other Relative:
<note place="margin">What this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is.</note> The Poſitive is either eſſential, as God is, whoſe Holineſs is his eſſence; or communicated, as is the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Saints and Angels, which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48970:26"/>conſiſts in poſitive habits of Holineſs inherent in them, and imparted to them by God, the fountain of Holineſs.
<note place="margin">Relative.</note> Relative Holineſs is ſo called, becauſe all ſuch Holineſs conſiſteth only in the Reference and Relation the things inveſted therewith, have to God, who is Holy, and to the Holy end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are deſtined.
<note place="margin">Common to perſons and things.</note> And this Holineſs was not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to men, but common to all other things that might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated and conſecrated to God. In this ſenſe men are often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Holy, either in regard of their Function, or ſome State and Condition which puts them in peculiar relation unto God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt reſpect, three ſorts of people were called Holy, Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets: Who therefore were ſolemnly Conſecrated with Holy Oyl, and termed God's annointed. In the other reſpect, all the firſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48970:26"/>born of men and beaſts, all vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, as <hi>Nazarites,</hi> were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Holy unto the Lord. Nor were men only thus Holy, but all other things that might be dedicated unto God, and were ſo, as all Places, Veſſels, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Times; all things, as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oyl, Tithes, Incenſe, Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Oblations, Vows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were in ſpecial order to God's Service, and thereto devoted; this is plain in the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Holineſs did not make the perſons, or the things Holy, by any poſitive Inherent Holineſs, by any Sanctifying Graces infuſed (for a man might be Holy in regard of his Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and yet unholy in his life; witneſs <hi>Hophny</hi> and <hi>Phine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi>) but by reaſon of the Holy Object, and the Holy end and uſe whereunto they had relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This latter Holineſs we aſcribe to Churches, and to all other things whatſoever given
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48970:27"/>to God, and ſet apart for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>Now that Churches have this Holineſs,
<note place="margin">Churches are relatively Holy proved.</note> I prove, 1. That pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Gods Worſhip, were Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all will grant: For 'twas a received maxim among thoſe Antients, that a place conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, did hallow the whole Country, and that the Land was unhallowed where there was no place ſet apart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.
<note place="margin">Joſh. 22.19.</note> Witneſs the ſtory of the Altar built by <hi>Gad</hi> and <hi>Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben,</hi> and the half Tribe upon the Banks of <hi>Jordan,</hi> which <hi>Joſhuah</hi> ſuppoſed they had built for this cauſe, leaſt the Lord of their poſſeſſion, being cut off from <hi>Canaan</hi> (where the Lord's Tabernacle was) by the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſo having no place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated therein to the Worſhip of their God, might be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean and unhallowed Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For ſo ſaith <hi>Phineas,</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48970:27"/>the Princes of the other Tribes, ſent to diſwade them, <hi>If the Land of your Poſſeſſion, be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God would have ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be reverenced. And therefore to ſhew he hath as much care of the place of his Worſhip, as of the time, being both equally Holy,
<note place="margin">Levit. 19.30</note> he enjoyns them both together, <hi>ye ſhall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my Sanctuaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remains that I prove pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under the Goſpel dedicated to God, to be likewiſe Holy,
<note place="margin">That ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under the Goſpel are Holy, proved.</note> though not with ſuch legal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and obſervations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Temple of the <hi>Jews</hi> was hallowed; yet with ſuch Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as they might not be any ways prophaned or diverted to common uſes.</p>
            <p>This I prove by our Saviours ſcourging out the Prophaners of the Temple, which that you may not think far fetched, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48970:28"/>from my purpoſe, conſider, 1. What part of the Temple this was. 2. The reaſons why he did ſo. 3. The time when.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">What part of the Temple our Saviour clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> It was neither the Inner-Temple, where the Prieſts alone came; nor the middle, where the <hi>Jews</hi> and Circumciſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites were permitted to bend; but the outward, which was common to all Nations that were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Parkers <hi>defence agriaſt</hi> J. O. <hi>p.</hi> 154.</note> Worſhippers of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though they did not tye themſelves to legal obſervances. This third, the <hi>Jews</hi> ſcarce accounted ſacred, the other two they did, and were ſo ſtrict, that no uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed perſon might enter into it, even at this time, when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour exerciſed his Authority. And in this Court did they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſell their Sheep and Oxen, at the Feaſt of the Paſſover, to ſuch as came far off to Sacrifice, and could not conveniently bring them with them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:48970:28"/>You ſee our Saviour vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the prophanation of this outmoſt Temple: And this is farther manifeſt by the place of Scripture quoted by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, which otherwiſe would be impertinent: <hi>My houſe ſhall be called a houſe of Prayer for all Nations; but ye have made it a den of Thieves.</hi> Now no part of this houſe, was a houſe of Prayer for the Prieſts and <hi>Jews:</hi> This then was the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles Oratory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note n="2" place="margin">The Reaſons</note> Why did our Saviour cleanſe this? Not becauſe it was a place of Legal Worſhip or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for ſo it was not; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, 1. It was a place dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God, it was his houſe. 2. Becauſe it was a place deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Prayer, a Holy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Act.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the time,
<note place="margin">The times.</note> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times that our Saviour did this; It was not only once, but twice. The firſt time he went
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48970:29"/>up to the Paſſover, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Prophetical, Office; and the ſecond time he went up to the Paſſover to finiſh that, and to enter upon his Prieſtly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and to put an end to Jewiſh Ceremonies. How unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble had it been to vindicate the violation of Typical and Legal Sanctity, which within few days after he was utterly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh by his Croſs, unleſs he meant to leave his Church a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Leſſon, what reverence and Reſpect he would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted due to ſuch places as this was, which he thus vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. For we find not in all the Goſpel, any other example of vindictive Authority uſed by our Saviour, but only this, in freeing his Fathers houſe from Prophanation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if this Argument be not ſufficient, add here to what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He that defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Temple of God, him will
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48970:29"/>God deſtroy.</hi> He ſpeaks indeed of the Bodies of Chriſtians, which are Temples of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or ſhould be: But the reaſon holds as well for other Material Temples, as well as their Bodies, which are ſo called Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorcally. For why will God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him that prophanes the Temple of his Body? Why, but becauſe God hath made it, and Conſecrated it to his own Uſe and Service; 'tis Gods Temple. If this be the reaſon, then it will hold for Churches likewiſe; for they are given and ſet apart for God, and for his alone uſe. They are his, not ours: and therefore to eſteem them as common, is to provoke God to deſtroy us, for ſuch our Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Prophanation.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The Apoſtle, where he forbids thoſe things to be done in the Church, which may be done in private houſes, as for women to ſpeak, to be uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48970:30"/>men to be covered, as alſo to eat there, their ordinary viands, and to do other ſuch common Actions, what doth he therein but argue the Sanctity of them, and their ſeparation from Prophane and Common uſes?</p>
            <p>If you ask when this Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Holineſs doth firſt begin to ſeparate ſuch places from common uſes:
<note n="2" place="margin">When this Holineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</note> I anſwer, at what time they are at firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated: For from that time they ſtand in relation to God. This may appear from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra,</hi> who for purloyning part of that, which they had only in their hearts vowed unto God, were convicted of Sacriledge, and for example ſtruck dead immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</p>
            <p>If you ask how long this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs laſts upon them;
<note n="3" place="margin">How long it laſts.</note> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſo long as the Relation which makes them Holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48970:30"/>upon them; that is till God ſhall give up his Intereſt and Right in them. Not only while Divine Duties are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therein, but ſo long as the place is in order to ſuch Holy uſe. As a Prieſt doth not loſe his Relative Holineſs in regard of his Function, after he is come out of the Church, and there executed his Office; ſo neither doth the Church: For a Prieſt is even as Holy when he is out of the Church, and hath finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Miniſtery, as when he is in the execution thereof. And this to have been the Nature of all other Sacred things, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Sanctity, as long as the Relation they have to God remained on them, I ſhall prove hereafter.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of outward Worſhip in God's Houſe; I proceed to ſhew the Lawfulneſs of ſpecifying or determining this outward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48970:31"/>towards ſome place therein, more than others Secondly, I will prove the Lawfulneſs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining our Worſhip towards this place, <hi>viz.</hi> the Altar, or Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Table. The Lawfulneſs of both I will prove two ways; 1. Negatively, by proving them to be neither Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor Superſtition, nor Will-Worſhip. 2. Affirmatively, by proving this Specification of our Worſhip to be conſonant to God's Word, and to the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Practiſe of the Saints in all Ages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">It is lawful to determine our Worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſome place.</note> It is lawful to ſpecify or determine our Worſhip of God in his houſe, to ſome place. 1. Becauſe it is neceſſary man ſhould tender his Worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſome place in ſpecial, it being a bodily Act, and he muſt look and bow one way, either to the right, or left; to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or lower end; unleſs he will turn round as he Worſhips, or
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48970:31"/>look nine ways at once, that he might not be thought to adore the place he bows toward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And to one place rather than another. which is no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</note> As our Worſhip muſt be done towards ſome place in ſpecial, ſo it is lawful to do it towards one place rather than another. 1. There is no Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in it; for unleſs we make the place the object of our Worſhip ſome ways, it is no Worſhip of an Idol: But we tender none of our Worſhip to the place. You may as well ſay we cannot look up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when we ſay our Prayers, but we muſt Worſhip the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. Beſides, if to Worſhip God towards one place rather than another, be Idolatry, then <hi>Daniel</hi> when he Worſhipped God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word the Temple, and the <hi>Jews</hi> when they worſhipped toward the Altar and Ark, committed I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. For if they could not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God toward one place more than nother, but they muſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48970:32"/>Worſhip the place, Certainly' God, who is Jealous of his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in point of Idolatry, would never have commanded or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it. What was then no Idolatry, cannot be now; for Idolatry is the ſame thing now and then, and the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment did alike concern them and us.</p>
            <p>And as there is no Idolatry,
<note place="margin">No ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſo there is no ſuperſtition in it: For we no ways circumſcribe God's Immenſity, or <hi>omni pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> or confine it to a place hereby, no more than <hi>Solomon</hi> did, when he built a Temple for him; or God himſelf did circumſcribe himſelf, when he commanded a Tabernacle to be ſet up for him to dwell in. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it in his heart, that men hereby ſhould have ſuch a conceit of him, as if he could be limited or contained in any place. Nor indeed had they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch conceipt, for ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48970:32"/>The Heaven of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens is not able to contain thee, how much leſs the houſe that I have built?</hi> Now, if we do not imagine that God cannot be confined to any Church, why ſhould any dream that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine him to ſome place in the Church more than another? Do you think God is confined in the Church, when you go out of your Houſes thither to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him? would you think well of them that ſhould ſo judge of you? Why ſhould you then judge of us that we tye God to one place in the Church, becauſe we worſhip him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward one place rather than another?</p>
            <p>Nor that it is Will-worſhip,
<note place="margin">Nor Will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> I ſhall prove by ſhewing it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to God's word, which thus I do:</p>
            <p>That which is decent and orderly,
<note place="margin">But Conſonant to Gods word.</note> is not only Conſonant to, but Commanded by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48970:33"/>But to Specify our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to one place is Decent and Orderly. <hi>Ergo.</hi> If the promiſcuous and in different Worſhip of God towards any place, left to every ones diſcretion, be indecent, and diſorderly, and a confuſion, then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of it to one place is Orderly and Decent. But <hi>&amp;c. Ergo.</hi> For tell me, is there any Order where there is not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and Uniformity? Is there any Conformity or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity that when Men come into the Church, one ſhould bow towards the Font, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward the Pulpit, a third towards the Table, a fourth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Windows, one one way and another another? Surely this is not Conformity or Uniformity, and therefore not Decency; and therefore a breach of the Apoſtles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and a diſorderly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the God of Order. If
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48970:33"/>any think this various worſhip Orderly, I ask, whether he thinks it would be orderly for one to come into the Church creeping, another going, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reeling, another dancing; one Covered, another bare? If not Order in this, neither in the other; for the Ground of Order is Uniformity: but there is no more Uniformity in ſuch Worſhip, than in ſuch coming into the Church.</p>
            <p>(2) It is Lawful to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our worſhip toward the Altar, or Holy Table.
<note place="margin">Lawful to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore towards<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Altar, proved Neg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</note> That it is neither Idolatry nor Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is apparent by what I ſaid before; for we neither tender any worſhip to the Table, nor Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribe Gods preſence there. When a man pulls off his Hat at his coming into the Church, he may as well be ſaid to adore the Stones or Walls, and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine Gods preſence there; for he doth not come into his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48970:34"/>own Houſe in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>And that it is not will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Affirmatively Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> I prove, becauſe it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the analogy of Faith, that requires our worſhip or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhould be reaſonable, and ſuch is this. For if we adore, Neceſſity enforceth us to bow to ſome place; Decency requires to bow to one place, and Reaſon would that place ſhould be the that fitteſt place.
<note place="margin">One place in the Church is more Holy then another.</note> Now the fitneſs of this place is to be judged by the Dignity and Excellency of it, and that is to be meaſured by the Degree of Relation it hath to God, and the Highneſs of the uſe, whereunto it is appointed. Now what part of all the Church, or what thing in the Church hath ſo near a Relation to God, as the Holy Table? or what is appointed for ſo high and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Uſe as that? That which hath a nearer relation to God,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48970:34"/>&amp; a higher uſe than other things, muſt needs participate of more External Sanctity, and Dignity than other things. Elſe you may ſay the Belfry is as Holy as the Pulpit, or Communion Table,
<note place="margin">The H. Table more Holy then the reſt.</note> and as excellent. But the H. Table hath nearer relation unto God, &amp; is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined to an higher uſe than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing in the Church, <hi>Ergo</hi> it is more Holy &amp; excellent, &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the fitteſt place to tender our Devotions toward.</p>
            <p>There is nothing likely to ſtand in competition with it,
<note place="margin">Than the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</note> but the Pulpit, or the Font; but neither of theſe have ſo near a Relation or ſo high an uſe Firſt the Pulpits digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty proceeds from the Word of God therein read or preached; but Gods Spirit hath not made ſo near a U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion between the word &amp; it ſelf, as the Son of God hath done at the Sacrcement celebrated on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</p>
            <p>As for the Font, True it is,
<note place="margin">Then the Fon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the Scripture calls it the Laver fo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, the New-birth, and that by the waſhing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48970:35"/>we receive remiſſion of Sins.
<note place="margin">Baptiſme the Analogy of it</note> But the Analogy of that Sacrament is only thus, that as in our firſt birth, when we come out of our Mothers Womb, we are waſhed from the pollutions thereof with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſo in our ſecond, or new birth, they that were born into the Church, and made Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame, were waſhed from the pollutions of their Sins, by the Sanctifying of the Holy Spirit, who in Holy Scripture is frequently Signified under the name of Water. <hi>John</hi> 7.38, 39.</p>
            <p>Now though our bleſſed Saviours death and blood-ſhed be the ground of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet it is not his Blood that is repreſented by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the Sanctifying of the Holy Spirit; whence our Saviour ſaid to <hi>Nicodemus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lhſs a man be born again of Water and of the Spirit.</hi> &amp;c</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:48970:35"/>Beſides Baptiſme is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of our Initiation, the Lords Supper, of our Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; Baptiſme might be Adminiſtred to Infants; the Lords Supper, only to men of Ripe years. By Baptiſme we have only the beginning of our Spiritual Life; by the Lords Supper we have our Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſervation in it, and Continual food and nouriſhment; This is the Commemoration, Repreſentation Exhibition, and Application, of that one moſt perfect Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our Lord, once offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Croſs; So that upon this Table is prepared God's Heavenly Banquet for our Souls, our <hi>Manna,</hi> the Bread of Life, in Compariſon whereof, all Earthly Feaſts and Dainties are but poor, Courſe, and deſpicable. From hence we drink the Cup of Salvation, and Heavenly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction; yea, we eat and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48970:36"/>drink the very Body and Blood of our Saviour in a Miſtery; Whence the Antient Fathers are wont to call them Reverend and Dreadful Myſteries, the Viands of Immortality, the earneſt of our Inheritance; and the place in Reference thereto, The Holy Altar, the Sacred Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Seat and Throne, and Chair of Eſtate of our Lord Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Thus I hope I have proved this Table to be the Higheſt and moſt Honourable part of the Church, and therefore the fitteſt, towards which our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions to God ſhould be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Now I ſhall prove it to be Conſonant to Scripture, and approved by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of the Saints in all Ages.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you expect ſome place of Scripture containing this Propoſition in expreſs terms; But this Demand were
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48970:36"/>unreaſonable; For if we ſhould believe no more than what we have expreſs words of Scripture for in the <hi>New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Then we ſhall be never able to prove our Baptizing of Infants,
<note place="margin">The Analogy of the H. T. a Rule in many things.</note> or our ſubſtituting the Lords day in place of the Jewiſh Sabbath, which are two points of main Conſequence; and yet we have no Rule given expreſly concerning them in the <hi>New-Teſtament:</hi> Nor was it needful; for in ſuch things where God hath not given, or preſcribed to us any new Rule to guide us,
<note place="margin">In Tithes.</note> he hath refered us to the Analogy of the <hi>Old,</hi> This the Apoſtle teacheth us, where he proves the due of the Miniſters, miantainance under the Goſpel from the Analogy of the Old Law, <hi>Do ye not know that they that Miniſter about Holy things live of the Holy things of the Temple,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 9.13.</note> and they that waitat the Altar, are Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48970:37"/>of the Altar? even ſo hath the Lord Ordained that they that preach the, Goſpel, would live of the Goſpel.</hi> But where hath God Ordained that, but in the Old Law, whence the Apoſtle proveth this? for what need God give a new Commandment concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tithes, in the <hi>New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> while the Reaſon and Ground of the Commandement firſt given, doth as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us as them? It was reaſon that they who waited at the Altar, ſhould live of it: It is as much reaſon that they who Preach the Goſpel, ſhould live by it. God hath reſerved to himſelf the Tithes to beſtow upon his Miniſters, in the <hi>Old-Teſtament,</hi> for their maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and it was not needful he ſhould give any new Command for Tithes under the Goſpel, ſeeing he never aboliſh't them; that he hath not aboliſh't them,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48970:37"/>is plain, becauſe he hath not aboliſh't the cauſe for which he did at firſt Ordain them, <hi>viz,</hi> the mainitainance of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as the Apoſtle here ſhews. Thus you ſee the folly of thoſe, that will admit of no proofs out of the <hi>Old-Teſtament,</hi> for any thing, even there where is the ſame ground and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes here by his own practice, and by citing a place out of <hi>Deuterinomy</hi> 25.4. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzel the mouth of the Oxe which treadeth out the Corn. which,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>God ſpake altogether for our ſakes that are Miniſters of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whence aroſe the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient practiſe of the Church in Baptiſing Infants,
<note place="margin">I Pedo Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and the Lords day</note> but from the Analogy of Circumciſion? or the Hallowing of every firſt day in the week, as one in ſeven, but from the Analogy of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48970:38"/>Jewiſh Sabath? By the ſame reaſon it was not neceſſary for God or Chriſt in the Goſpel to give us any new rule for the manner of our worſhip of him in his houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. line</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 14 <hi>Ir. line line</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 3.</note> or to ſpecify the place to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards which we ſhould Adore him, in expreſs words, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein left us to the Anal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogy of the Old Law, there being the ſame reaſon to tye us to worſhip God towards this place, that there was to tye the <hi>Jews,</hi> to worſhip him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Altar; I might alledge to this purpoſe a place out of <hi>Clemens</hi> (a man of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique age, and whoſe name, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> was written in the Book of Life) in his true and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> We p. 52. where he ſaith, ought to do all things right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and orderly, which our Lord hath Commanded us to Celebrate, our oblations and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgyes at appointed times; for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48970:38"/>he would not have theſe things done raſhly, and out of order, but at ſet times and hours. He hath likewiſe defined by his moſt High will, where and by whom he would have theſe things performed. But where I pray do we find any of theſe things Specified by God, unleſs he hath left us to the Analogy of the <hi>Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the only reaſon that moved the <hi>Jews</hi> to worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Ark was the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of his Name, that is,
<note place="margin">The ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ties us to wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhip God towards the Altar, that tied the Jews to worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Ark.</note> of his Special preſence. The whole Temple was the Place of Gods Special Preſence, but the Ark was (as it were) his Front or Face, where he did moſt chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtify his Preſence,
<note place="margin">Simil.</note> as the whole Chamber, where the King manifeſts himſelf to his Subjects, is called the Preſence Chamber, but the Chair of Eſtate doth moſt principally repreſent the Kings Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:48970:39"/>But firſt I will ſhew that places in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> ſet a part for Gods Worſhip, were places ſet a part for the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of his Name, and therefore Sacred; and alſo that God did promiſe a ſpecial Exhibition of his preſence and bleſſings in thoſe places. This I prove out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. where God, after the promulgation of the Decalogue, forbidding the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by <hi>Moſes,</hi> to make with him gods of Silver and Gold, but that they make him an Altar of Earth (ſuch as their Condition then permitted, while they were journeying into the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land, afterwards of Stone) and thereon Sacrifice their burnt Offerings; he adds, <hi>In all places where I Record my Name</hi> (that is, where I cauſe the memorial, monument or remembrance of my Special preſence to be) <hi>thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I come to thee, and Bleſs thee.</hi> The memorial or monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48970:39"/>of His Name is a Token or Symbole whereby he teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his preſence, Covenant and Commerce with man. Of theſe the Jews had two in ſpecial; Firſt, the Altar with their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices on it, whereat God did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten manifeſt himſelf by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming the Sacrifice, and was always preſent. For this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, here ſpoken of, was made before ever the Ark was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or before there was any Command for making of it; And therefore before the Ark of the Teſtimony was made, they did Exhibit their Reverence and Worſhip towards the Altar. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, when the Ark was made, as a ſtanding monument and memorial, they tendred their worſhip toward that, and the Altar joyntly; For the Ark was within the Vail,
<note place="margin">Exod. 30.6.</note> and the Altar before the Vail, without: And that the Sacrifices upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar was called likewiſe the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48970:40"/>is apparent by the 2.5.6. and 24. Chapt. of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> But the cheif Memorial, after it was appointed and made by God, was the Ark of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant or Teſtimony, which was therefore ſet within the Vail.
<note place="margin">Things are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent degrees of Relative Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> (which by the way, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues that things are capable of deffrent degrees of Relative ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs thereafter, as they ſhall have a nearer, or farther Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God; and participate a leſs, or more holy uſe; whence the deſtinction was of Holy, and moſt Holy in the Temple and Tabernacle) Again, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial a memorial of God was the Ark, that it was called by Gods very Name. Hence the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins,</hi> when they heard that the Ark,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.7.</note> was brought into the Camp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the ſhouting of the People, they ſaid, God is come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Camp, meaning the Ark, which was the Symbole of Divine preſence. But more epecially,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48970:40"/>it is thrice called by the Name of <hi>Jehovah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.5.14.21.</note> where <hi>David</hi> is ſaid to dance before the Lord, before <hi>Jehovah,</hi> when yet it was but before the Ark.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 47.6. 2 Sam. 6.15.</note> So likewiſe God is gone up with a ſhout, and the Lord with a ſound of a Trumpet, when the Ark was carried up out of the Land of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> and brought into the City of <hi>David,</hi> by <hi>David,</hi> with the ſhouting and the ſound of the Trumpet. <hi>Phinehas</hi> wife called it the Glory. i. e. The place of Gods Glorious preſence. The Glory is departed from <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.22.</note> for the Ark of God is taken.</p>
            <p>Now that God hath as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a Memorial of his Name among us in our Churches, as the Ark, I ſhall eaſily prove. For did not Chriſt ordain the Euchariſt to be a Memorial of his Name among us Chriſtians, when he ſaith, <hi>This is my Body, do this in Rimembrance of me?</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:48970:41"/>Did God ever ſay more to the <hi>Jews,</hi> to argue his ſpecial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, either at their Altar or their Ark, then what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath ſaid of the Sacrament, <hi>This is my Body, i. e.</hi> My Perſon is myſtically united to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and therefore Expreſly calls it his Memorial.
<note place="margin">Our Memorial more Eminent then their.</note> Why ſhould not the places then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the Station of this Memorial under the Goſpel, have as great Sanctity as that, whereby Gods Name was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Law? What had the Jewiſh Memorial to make it Holy, which is not Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, nay, excelled by the Chriſtians? Is not Chriſts Body better than their <hi>Manna?</hi> Are not our Goſpels better than their Tables? Ask Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Who makes a compariſon between the Law and the Goſpel, and from the Excellency thereof, concludes the dignity of our Miniſtery above the Jewiſh, in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48970:41"/>as much as they were Miniſters only of the Letter, we of the Spirit. Now what had the Ark to make it ſo Holy, more than the <hi>Manna,</hi> and the two Tables? and why then ſhould not our Goſpels, and our Sacrament placed on the Altar far ſurpaſs them, and dignify the Table a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Ark.</p>
            <p>Our Sacrament,
<note place="margin">Our Memiral Obj. all is uos ever preſent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Alter.</note> the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Memorial is not preſent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Table, as <hi>Manna,</hi> and the Tables were in the Ark.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> It is not neceſſary it ſhould be, it is ſufficient, they are wont to be there, and that the place is appropriated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. As the Chair of State lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not its Relation to the King, and reſpect is done to Him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it; though he be abſent Moreover note, that the Ark of the Covenant was not then in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when <hi>Daniel</hi> opened his window to pray thitherward, and that the ſacred Cabinet,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48970:42"/>with the things contained therein was wanting all the time of the Second Temple, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead whereof they made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to repreſent it.</p>
            <p>You ſee then, that according to the Analogy of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> we are as much bound to Adore God towards our Holy Table, as they toward their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar or the Ark: The only rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they tendred their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion that way, being, for that it was Gods Memorial or place of ſpecial preſence: And becauſe we have as Sacred a Memorial of Gods preſence and Covenant, as they had, we have the ſame, nay, greater reaſon to oblige us to Worſhip towards this place, this being far more holy than theirs.</p>
            <p>Again, as God promiſed to meet the <hi>Jews</hi> at ſuch places, where he did record His Name, and there bleſs them. The ſame promiſe is made to us by our
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48970:42"/>Saviour',
<note place="margin">Math. 18.22.</note> 
               <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my Name, there I will be in the midſt of them.</hi> Where take notice of a ſpecial prenſence; For Chriſt is every where, in Him we live, we move, and have our being; He is never from us, and therefore if there were not a promiſe of a ſpecial preſence, what great matter had there been in our Saviours words? And to what purpoſe were that preſence, but to meet with them and bleſs them? Now if Chriſt hath promiſed this in every place, where men are aſſembled in his Name, that is, to Praiſe and Glorify his Name in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, how much more in that place where his Name is perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually recorded, and that by his own appointment? For a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial promiſe of Gods bleſſing and meeting us when we call upon him, and bow to Him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this place, doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:48970:43"/>Gods bleſſing to the place no more than that promiſe to the <hi>Jews,</hi> did hinder Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them in the Houſe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> and in the field, in their going out and coming in, which he promiſed, if they obeyed.</p>
            <p>Or think you, when <hi>David</hi> ſaid, Hear the Voice of my Humble Petition when I cry unto thee, when I hold up my hands towards the Mercy Seat of thy Holy Temple, That he thought God could not, or would not hear him any where elſe? Or that <hi>Solomon</hi> thought God could not, or would not hear any prayer but what was made in his Temple? certainly he did not. For the reaſon why he beſeeched God to have reſpect unto the Place which he had made, and to hear the Prayers of thoſe that prayed in it, or towards it, was only this, becauſe it was built for the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of Gods Name, for the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48970:43"/>place of his ſpecial preſence, and God had promiſed to place his Name there. And mark Gods Anſwer, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 7.14.
<note place="margin">2 Chr. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>If my People ſhall humble themſelves and Pray,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then will I hear and forgive. Now mine eyes ſhall be open and mine ears attent to the Prayert that are made in this place.</hi> Would you know the reaſon why God would hear in this place rather than in another? (Though God did not abridge himſelf of hearing in anyother place) It is expreſly ſet down in the next Verſe, <hi>For now I have choſen and Sanctified this houſe, that my Name,</hi> (that is my Memorial, or ſpecial preſence) <hi>might be there for ever, and my Eyes and my Heart ſhall be there perpetually.</hi> Is there not the ſame reaſon for Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in our Churches, as in their Temple? if they be as much Sanctified to this end, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods Memorial, or Name to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48970:44"/>in, as that was? And to what other end were theſe ever Conſecrated?</p>
            <p>Now, unleſs you can ſhew this promiſe of Gods meeting and bleſſing men by a peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in all places where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded his Name, was proper to the <hi>Jews,</hi> or hath been ſince reverſed by God, then certainly our Churches have as much of Gods ſpecial preſence as the Temple; And God will there meet with us, and bleſs us e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially; and we are to adore God as much towards our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, as the <hi>Jews</hi> towards theirs.</p>
            <p>Thus I have proved the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Adoration towards the Altar, out of Scripture. Now for the Opinion, and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Church.</p>
            <p>That it was the Opinion, and Practiſe of the Old Church,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.22. 2 Kings 19.14. 2 Chr. 7.3.</note> is apparent by what is ſaid <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> in his diſtreſs went into
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48970:44"/>the Temple, and their Prayed towards the Place of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>Viz.</hi> the Mercy Seat, and therefore compellates God by this Title, <hi>Thou that dwelleſt between the Cherubims.</hi> Might not the King have Prayed at home? was not God preſent in his houſe? or had he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined him between the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims? No, but <hi>Hezekiah</hi> knew that God had more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially promiſed his Preſence in this Place, and therefore here he comes, and proſtrates himſelf before Gods Memorial.</p>
            <p>How the Chriſtians Eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ever and reverenced their Churches, <hi>Vid. &amp;c.</hi> And how highly they regarded their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, <hi>Chriſoſt. Hom.</hi> 20. In the Second Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians. Optatus</hi> in his 6th. Book, deſcribing the Dignity of the Altar, illuſtrates it from this, <hi>Viz.</hi> That it was the Seat of the Body and Blood of Chriſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48970:45"/>
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> falling down at the foot of the Altar, beſought God that he would ſubvert the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Plots and Endeavours of the <hi>Arrians;</hi> the next day <hi>Arrius,</hi> as he was exonerating nature, withal voided his Guts and Bowels, <hi>Nazians. Or.</hi> p. 1. or in ſome 25. tells, That his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> being Sick, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies her ſelf to the chief Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian of all mortals, and caſting her ſelf down before the Altar, and Invocating him who was Honoured upon the ſame, ſhe recovered her former health. By which Examples, it may ſeem that God, by his miraculous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, hath confirmed this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence. <hi>Tertull,</hi> tells how pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, after they are reſtored to the Church, at their entrance into it, were wont to caſt themſelves down before the Prieſts (from whom they were to receive abſolution) and to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48970:45"/>bow themſelves ſubmiſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God cares not for any comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, He requires the Heart,
<note place="margin">Object.</note> and the Inward Devotion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo our Saviour teacheth us to ſerve God,
<note place="margin">John. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>The hour cometh, and now is, that they that worſhip the Father, muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Text is much abuſed, to prove that God, in the Goſpel, allows not of External or Bodily worſhip or Service, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires this of the Spirit only, and conſequently to make this the main difference between Gods worſhip under the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> and the <hi>New.</hi> Now, firſt, I will ſhew the abſurdity of this meaning which they give of the words, and then declare the true ſenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:48970:46"/>This ſenſe is inconſequent from our Saviours Words;
<note place="margin">The abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> for he did not ſpeak any thing to the woman about Bodily wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but only about the place of worſhip, and the Object. For her queſtion to our Saviour (perceiving him to be a Prophet) was about a main controverſy between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> (who were bitter Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies) about the Place of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;
<note place="margin">They miſtake the Scope.</note> ſo whether Mount <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizim</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were the place appointed for Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? This you may ſee is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning the manner of worſhip, whether it ſhould be Outward or Inward. But our Saviour, in anſwering, waves the queſtion, and tells her, that was not ſo material a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, but that there was a greater Queſtion than that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the place, <hi>Viz.</hi> about the object of their worſhip; for you, ſaith he, worſhip you
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48970:46"/>know not what, but we <hi>Jews</hi> know what we worſhip. After which, follows the words cited, <hi>But the hour cometh,</hi> &amp;c. This is the firſt abſurdity, it hath not Conſiſtance with the conteſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They add to the Letter.</note> Their interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on addeth to the very Letter of the Text; For our Saviour ſaith not, we muſt worſhip him in Spirit (only,) there is no ſuch word. This excluſive particle our Saviour uſeth not: So that though he might mean, that we muſt worſhip him cheifly, or Principally in Spirit, yet it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not, but we might worſhip him with our bodies alſo Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately, for the Principal doth not exclude the Subordinate, but include it: And none dare ſay, that outward worſhip is oppoſite to inward. This is the Second Abſurdity; they add to the letter what our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour never ſaid or thought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This Expoſition is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48970:47"/>directly contrary to the words; For our Saviour ſaith, God muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and Truth; but God is not, nor yet can be worſhipped in Truth without Bodily worſhip; for his worſhip is not true,
<note place="margin">'Tis conerary to the Doctrine and practiſe of Chriſt, and of all Chriſtians in all Ages.</note> unleſs it be entire and Univerſal, as hath been ſhewen: and entire it is not, without the Joynt-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> This Expoſition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the Ordinances of the Goſpel expreſly, together with the practiſe of our Saviour, his Apoſtles, and the Church in all Ages; For the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are External Rites and Services. Baptiſme, wherein we make our firſt Stepulation with God, to become his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; The Euchariſt which is ſubſtituted in place of thoſe Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Sacrifices of the Law, to be a Rite and mean of our Addreſs; to Invocate and give thanks to his Father in the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:48970:47"/>are they not External Ceremonies and Services? Did not the Apoſtles, and the whole Church then, and the whole Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, ſupplicate God the Father by this Rite? They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued breaking of Bread (<hi>i. e.</hi> in the uſe of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and Prayers: And Therefore in the Primitive Church, they uſed to ſay all the Service at the Altar, to Signify that they ſent up their prayers in the Name of him, whoſe Sacrifice, the Ground of all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement and Interceſſion, was in that place Exhibited and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorated; yet it ſeems ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Novel to us, to have part of our Service read there.</p>
            <p>But leaſt you might ſay, the meaning is, not that God will have no External Service, but he will be worſhipped by no External Geſtures or Poſtures, I ſay this alſo contradicts our Saviours Practiſe, who himſelf
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48970:48"/>lifted up his Sacred Eyes to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; when helprayed for <hi>Lazarus,</hi> fell on his Face when he Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed in his Agony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What was Impoſition of hands, but an External geſture, when God was invoked by way of benediction? beſides, I ſee no reaſon, why, in the point of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical worſhip, Geſture ſhould be more excepted againſt than Voice; Is not Confeſſing, Praying, Praiſing, an External Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily worſhip, as well as that of Geſture? why then ſhould the one derogate from the worſhip of the Father in Spirit and Truth, and not the other? In a word, there never was yet in the World, any Society of men, that worſhipped the Father in ſuch a manner as this interpretation doth emply, and therefore this cannot be the meaning.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour intends here to reprehend the Idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The true ſence</note> who
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48970:48"/>worſhpped they knew not what, <hi>Viz.</hi> God under the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of a Dove, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Jeroboams</hi> time, and long after, under the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of a Calfe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans <hi>Idol.</hi>
               </note> This was the Object of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as appears out of the writings of the Jewiſh Rabbies. This was their Idolatry, they worſhipped God in a Bodily ſhape; and the reaſon which our Saviour gives, ſeems to emply this; For God (ſaith he) is a Spirit, <hi>i. e.</hi> he hath no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor is he ſuch, therefore he muſt be worſhipped as a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for ſo indeed he is; and not by any bodily Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>So that the ſenſe here is this, The hour cometh, and now is, that the true worſhippers ſhall Worſhip the Father in Spirit, (that is, conceiving of him no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than in Spirit) and in Truth, that is, not under any
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:48970:49"/>Corporal or Viſible ſhape; for thoſe that Worſhip under any Corporal ſimilitude, do indeed belye him: For the Apoſtle ſaith of ſuch, as changed the Glory of the Incorruptible God, into an Image made like to Corruptible man,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> they changed the truth of God into a lye. Hence Idols alſo are called Lyes, <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.4.</p>
            <p>Some interpret theſe words (the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip God in Spirit that is, no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by Jewiſh Ceremonies, but in and by Chriſt, who is the ſubſtance of thoſe ſhadows. This ſence, though it be true, and plauſible, yet it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous to our Saviours reaſon; <hi>For God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a Spirit, and muſt be,</hi> &amp;c. If this be the reaſon, then God ſhould never have been worſhipped with Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Ceremonies and Rites; for God was a Spirit from the beginning, and manifeſted himſelf ſo to be, even to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48970:49"/>Worſhipped him with Rites and Ceremonies. Therefore I adhere to my firſt ſenſe, Thus your main Fort is blown up.</p>
            <p>The Second Objection drawn from Goos Proteſtation againſt Sacrifices, <hi>Michel.</hi> 6.6, 7, 8. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51. with the Anſwer, <hi>Vid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, Religion, as man hath both a Body and Soul, the Soul of our Service is the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Soul; but the Body of that Soul, is the Service of our Body; one muſt inform the other, and both make a compleat man of God. For as the Body without the Soul is dead, ſo the Soul without the Body is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. God loves no maimed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, God calls for the Heart, becauſe he knows it commands the whole Man, and therefore if he have the Heart at his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he is ſure of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:48970:50"/>Obj. <hi>Suppoſe all this, God is to be adored outwardly as well as inward ly; Yet this manner of Adoration is Dangerous, and may become ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways Evil. For,</hi> 1. <hi>It is Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to weak brethren, who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at are offended.</hi> 2. <hi>It may be an occaſion to ſome Ignorant Ones to Commit Idolatry, by Adoring the very Table.</hi> 3. <hi>It is a fair Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to Popiſh Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Every Scandal or offence taken, is not a Scandal given; Therefore that is properly called Scandalous, which in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tends to give offence, not that which through willfulneſs or blindneſs, may, by accident, become ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reſp.</note> Was not Chriſt himſelf a Scandal and Rock of offence? to the <hi>Jews,</hi> a Stumbling-block? to the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſs? was not his Croſs a Scandal? ſhould not therefore Chriſt have come and been Crucified, becauſe this proved an occaſion of Scandal?
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48970:50"/>but who are theſe weak Ones? and how is this an offence?</p>
            <p>For the weak Ones,
<note place="margin">Who are the weak.</note> they are ſuch as uſually think themſelves ſtrongly grounded in the Faith, and able to confute this Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we here maintain: Such as though they be Women and Weavers, think they can teach twenty of us thred-bare Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for all our Learning. Theſe are the weak Ones forſooth, weak I confeſs in their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for they are blind, and therefore the bolder; but in their own conceipt ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p>But how are theſe offended?
<note place="margin">Why are they offended.</note> Are they drawn to imitate us, in our Worſhip waveringly, and doubtingly, not knowing, (through the weakneſs of their Judgment) whether they ſin or no,
<note place="margin">Scandal.</note> but relying on the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſcience of him whom they imitate, thereby enſnare their conſciences in ſin?
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48970:51"/>This is properly a Scandal,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.</note> as the Apoſtle ſhews expreſly, were he makes that a Scandal given, when in a thing in it ſelf indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, as Eating of meat Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to Idols, not as ſuch, but as bought in the Market by a man of knowledge; who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that meat commendeth not to God, and takes no notice of the Idol to whom it was offered, but Eats is as Common, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary. When, I ſay, this Act of him that hath knowledge, doth occaſion one weak in knowledge, to Eat the ſame meat with conſcience of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, grounding himſelf upon the example of him, whom he imitates, and ſo offends, Thus then comes in the Scandal. The ſtrong Eat of that without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Idol, among the weak or ignorant that know not how to make ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction; They imitate the ſtrongs example, as thinking
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48970:51"/>what is lawful for the ſtrong, is lawful for them, and ſo Eat of it with conſcience of the Idol, or as devoted to an Idol, which is Idolatry. Thus the ſtrongs knowledge is an occaſion of Sandal to the weak, that is, it makes the weak offend in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that without faith and know ledge, which the ſtrong do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faith and knowledge. But do theſe weak ones imitate us there in, and Worſhip God in this manner? They had rather run to <hi>New England,</hi> than make a legg towards the Altar in the <hi>Old.</hi> How are they then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended? I'le tell you, they are vext at it, they Rail upon us for it, they Calumniate us for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, they Scoff at us as Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and Foppiſh, and thus they are offended.</p>
            <p>Again, there is a great deal of difference between Adoreing God towards the moſt fitting place in his Houſe (which I have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48970:52"/>already proved a neceſſary part of Divine Worſhip) and a thing indifferent, which in its own nature may prove a Scandal, as the Eating of meat Sacrificed to Idols, and the like. For then we ſhould do no part of Divine Worſhip, leaſt ſome ſhould imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate us to do it amiſs: We ſhould not come to the Lords Supper; becauſe ſome that are ignorant come thither only for faſhion, becauſe they ſee others do it, and underſtand not what it is, and wherefore: They think it lawful for them to do as their betters and wiſer do, and ſo they Eat unworthily and ignorantly, which others do worthily and in faith, and ſo offend in and by others knowledge. What then? Is the Sacrament and the Eating thereof a Scandal? No, what's the reaſon? becauſe in it ſelf, it tends not to make men offend by unworthy receiving. 2. It is no matter of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48970:52"/>3. Becauſe thoſe that are ignorant and weak, are ſo wilfully, having means to be better inſtructed and informed. So is it in this caſe, this Worſhip of God, I have proved a thing Neceſſary, not Arbitrary. 2. In it ſelf it tends not to make any offend, either by Worſhipping the Table, or the place we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip towards: For then God ſhould have done all, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting and approving ſuch Worſhip amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom he would by no means put upon any ocoaſion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Idolatry, to which they were to prove of themſelves. 3. There are none but have means to be better inſtructed; therefore if any be offended, God forgive them, and ſend them more wit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ignorant may be ſeduced or miſled to worſhip the Table,
<note place="margin">The Ignorant may be ſeduced:</note> or place it ſelf, or to tye God to one place more than another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:48970:53"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection is part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered in my diſcourſe of Scandal. Now I ſay, 1. A good and neceſſary Duty muſt not be omitted, becauſe ſome may make ill uſe of it. 2. 'Tis a thing very unlikely, that any ſhould think we Worſhip the Table, when we Bow before it, and ſo imitate us in that, any more than they ſhould think, when we put of our Hats com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Church, that we Adore the Stones or Walls.</p>
            <p>It was the Ancient reproach of the Gentiles to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they worſhipped the Sun, becauſe they Adored God towards the Altar, which was ſet at the Eaſt end of their Churches: As alſo, that they Eat mans fleſh, and drank mans blood, becauſe they did Eat and Drink the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Should the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have left of theſe Duties,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48970:53"/>becauſe malice or ignorance might make ſuch conſtructions thereof? But what if it be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome ignorant men will A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Table? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſerve we that are Miniſters, but to inſtruct them better, and to inform them how, and in what manner they ought to ſerve God both in Body and Soul? what elſe is our Errand? what the end of our Preaching? Is it not to teach men the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Good and Evil? Right and Wrong? and to do <hi>Bonum vene?</hi> Thoſe that may be ſeduced, are to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</p>
            <p>Obj. 3.
<note place="margin">This opens a dore to Popery.</note> 
               <hi>They tend to bring in Popery, and lead us unto other things that are Popiſh and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Tis not Popiſh in it ſelf.</note> There is not the leaſt Popery in this. 2. There is no juſt fear of bringing it in by this. 1. The Papiſts do not Adore God before the Altar,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48970:54"/>but the Hoſt and Crucifix ſet upon the Altar, and make that the Immediate and formal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Adoration, <hi>viz.</hi> Their God Almighty in a Box, or piece of Wafer-Cake, which they ſay is the true Body and Blood of Chriſt. Moreover, when they Adore Images, they ſay, They do not Adore them, but thoſe whom the Images Repreſent,
<note place="margin">Image worſhip.</note> and put them in mind of. Now, they grant that they Adore the Image relatively, or tranſitively, though not ultimately or cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and therefore they Worſhip the thing repreſented in and by, and with the Image. This I ſpeak, becauſe ſome ſay the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have as good excuſe for their worſhipping of Images, as we have for our Adoration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar. Whereas we ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſclaim any kind of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to the Altar any ways, we make it no Object of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip either Relative or Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:48970:54"/>We make it no Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of God, we Worſhip not God in it, nor by it, nor with it, but only towards and before it, becauſe it is the fitteſt place for us to tender our Service of God towards, being the place of his Memorial in a ſpecial manner, and conſequently of his preſence. We diſclaim all Popiſh deſtinctions, and in no wiſe make the Table the Object of our Worſhip: Nor herein is our Proteſtation contrary to our Action; for if the Action, in its own nature, were Idolatrous, it had been ſo in the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither doth it introduce Popery. For the <hi>Lutherans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not apt to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce it.</note> who are bitter Enemies to the Papiſts, and the Papiſts to them, do obſerve this ſacred Rite: Nay, the Papiſts love and like us the worſe for it. For they baſely belying us, ſay, we Adore the Table, which they do not, but God who is upon it; and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:48970:55"/>us of worſe Idolatry than we do them; as if we worſhipt a Table, and made that our God. But they Slaunderouſly and Malitiouſly traduce us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowledge. To Idolize the Table, we abhor and deteſt, and no man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, except blinded with malice and prejudice, as they are, will believe them.</p>
            <p>You ſee how far this is from bringing in Popery. The truth is,
<note place="margin">This vaine fear begets the other extream.</note> this vain fear makes us to run into almoſt as great an abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for we are all for extreams. Becauſe men will not be Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious with the Papiſts, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt be Prophane, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious and Irreverent with the Puritans. Becauſe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Worſhip God falſely, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not Worſhip him after a true and due manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to his Word. Becauſe they Superſtitiouſly adorn their Churches, therefore we muſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48970:55"/>let them lye like Barns, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, nay, rather Sties. I am aſhamed to think that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, People of worth and faſhion, ſhould eſteem the Church, though never ſo ſqualid, ugly and deformed, the Windows broke, the Roof untiled and Leaking, the Walls hung with Cobwebs, broken, patch't and ill-favoured, the Holy Table ſtanding like an Alehouſe Table, either with out a Carpet, or with ſuch a one, as a man would ſcarce wipe his ſhoes withall, a Scurvy, Lowſy, Moth-eaten tattered piece of Darnix, or other cloth: That men of worth ſhould eſteem this place handſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſerve God in, to Feaſt with God in, to be partakers of his Holy Supper in, who would think high ſcorn to be no better accomodated in their private Houſes and Parlours. Would they think theſe things hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome at home? how then can
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:48970:56"/>they think them handſome in Gods Houſe? I appeal to the Reader, whether many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Kichens be not handſomer and better adorned than many Churches? I wonder what ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly god theſe men fancy to themſelves, that can be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be no better accomodated in his Houſe, than with that which they themſelves in their own Houſes count ugly and unſeemly. If it were but for this one piece of ſlovenly Devotion, I ſhould love naſty Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaniſme the worſe while I lived. I pray God amend ſuch horrible prophaneſs and abuſe.
<note place="margin">Why we make Obeyſence when we come into the Church.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why muſt we make courteſy when we come into the Church? can we not ſtay till we come to our Pews, and then fall down to our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why do we when we come into our Neighbours Houſe, before we ſpeak to him, put of our Hats, and then ſay by your leave?
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:48970:56"/>Gods peace be here? Why did our Saviour command his Diſciples when they entered into a Houſe to ſalute it? is it ſeemly and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſalute a mans Houſe, when we come into it, and is it not much more ſeemly to expreſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and Obeyſance to God, when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es foot into his?</p>
            <p>Obj.
<note place="margin">But it troubles my Devotion.</note> 
               <hi>But this will trouble my Devotions, diſtract my thoughts, and hinder my inward Reverence, while I am thinking of making a Leg or Courteſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Tuſh, never fear it, I'le warrant you no ſuch matter. Is there ſo much art to be uſed in making a Leg or Courtiſy, that it muſt needs trouble your thoughts; and put out of your mind the inward Reverence and thought of God? This were ſtrange! Let me ask one Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth Sighing and looking Sadly, and Weeping, hinder your Grief? Doth a merry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance hinder your Joy? Doth
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48970:57"/>paleneſs and trembling hinder your fear? Do your outward ſigns of Love hinder the Love of your Heart? Nay, rather, Do not theſe outward Actions increaſe and perfect the inward paſſions, which ſhew forth themſelves in them? why then ſhould Reverence, which is likewiſe a Paſſion, being mixt of Love which looks at God as good; and fear which looks at his Greatneſs, why, I ſay, ſhould this be hindred by the outward bowing of the Body, more than any other paſſion? Nay, why ſhould it not rather perfect and increaſe it? Why ſhould it not make us think and ſay, how dreadful and Reverend is this place? this is ſurely none other but the Houſe of God, and Gate of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Doth it diſtract the inward reſpect of Children to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to give them outward Reverence? to kneel to to them
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:48970:57"/>and ask them bleſſing? Doth it not make them rather have an higher and greater eſteem of them? Why then ſhould it not be ſo between God our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father and us? Nay, why ſhould it diſtract our Devotion more to bow to God when we come into the Church, than to kneel in our Pews? I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the one more than the other.</p>
            <p>Were God to be ſeen with bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes, or did he expreſs ſome viſible ſign of Glory, as he did to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſometimes in a thick cloud, ſometimes in a ſhineing light, then we would all fall down with fear and Reverence, and why, but becauſe of Gods Preſence? who yet is no more in ſuch a ſymbole or ſign, than he is in our Churches. For God is not viſible, nor were it lawful for us to worſhip ſuch a ſign, but him whoſe preſence is manifeſted thereby; though we
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48970:58"/>have no extraordinary ſign of his Preſence, yet as I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we have a ſtanding ſign and Memorial of his preſence, and he is as much to be ſeen in this as in that, for he is not viſible in either. Is it not then our want of faith, who are wholly immerſed and drowned in ſenſe, that we will not worſhip God unleſs we ſee him with our Eyes, or elſe ſome extraordinary Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſign of Him?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Yet for all this, what needs ſo much Cringing,
<note place="margin">Why bow to the Altar eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time we come by it.</note> and Bowing, and Ducking, and Adoring when we come in, and when we come out, and and as oft as we come before the Holy Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why do Parents bring up their Children and Servants to ſhew Reverence to them, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they come by them, or go in and out before them? Is there not as much reaſon that we ſhould be as obſervant of God our Maker and Redeemer,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48970:58"/>in his Houſe, by giving him hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dutiful worſhip towards the place of his Holineſs, Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and ſpecial preſence? I appeal to your ſelves, either it is Idleneſs in you to bring up your Children ſo, or no ſuperſtition in us to Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence God in this manner, as oft as we come before him &amp; approach near him. Whether you are more to be Reverenced by your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Children, than God our Lord and Father by us his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Children, ſpeak you.</p>
            <p>Obj.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Shew it in the</hi> Canon <hi>or</hi> Rubrick.</note> 
               <hi>But why ſhould we do that which is not commanded neither in the Canons, nor the Rubrick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Although it be not Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any where, yet the</hi> 7th. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <hi>of thoſe made</hi> 1640. <hi>commends it to the practice of all good people.</hi>
               </note> Why ſhould you rail at thoſe for doing of that which was never forbidden either in Canon, or <hi>Rubrick?</hi> But I anſwer, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why this is omitted in our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy is, becauſe at that time when that was compoſed and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, our Church thought it ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, to make any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, becauſe it was then a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48970:59"/>Catholick and received cuſtom ſo to do; and they did not think any Chiſtian would be ſo Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as to refuſe and diſlike it.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Organs in Cathedrals, for Anthems and Hymns, for the Rite of breaking the Bread and pouring out the Wine when the Prieſt pronounceth the words of Conſecration, yet all theſe are, and ever were piouſly done and uſed in our Church, without any explicite command or Injunction of the Church; and are ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded by the alone force and Virtue of the Catholick cuſtom of the Church, which carries with it the force of an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Law.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that our Church doth allow, and in a manner com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it, doth appear both in that this was never expunged out of divers Colledge Statutes, (which do expreſly enjoyn it) at that time when all our Statutes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48970:59"/>were purged and reformed, and alſo becauſe many Sacred Rites &amp; Forms ſtill uſed at the Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Kings, and by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Kingdom preſcribed, do enjoyn this Adoration: for in them the King himſelf, as alſo the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> is Commanded often humbly and lowly to adore God towards the Altar; and alſo may be further inferred from the preſcibed forms of Service for the Knights of the Garter, at the time of their Inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, wherein they are enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lowly and reverently to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore God towards the Altar at leaſt Twenty times while the Sacred Solemnities are Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently tranſacted.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Ancianes Adored to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the</hi> Eaſt, <hi>but why to the Altar?</hi>
               </note> To this add the conſtant practice of almoſt all our Cathedral Churches ever ſince our Reformation, which doth argue at leaſt an Implicite Command.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>If you ſtand ſo much upon Antiquity, the Ancients worſhipped
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48970:60"/>God towards the Orient; and this</hi> Juſtin Martyr <hi>in his Anſwer to</hi> 118th. <hi>Queſtion, affirmeth to have been a Tradition received from the very Apoſtles. Why then ſhould we tye our worſhip ſo much towards the Altar?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Worſhipping Towards the</hi> Eaſt. <hi>Why</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then it follows that the Ancients did ſpecificate their worſhip towards one place, which is much ſcrupled at. But they worrſhipped towards the Orient, becauſe the Altar ſtood there, and ſo they tendred their worſhip to God towards both jointly, and therefore towards the Eaſt becauſe the H. Table ſtood there. Now the reaſons why the ſcite of the Churches were <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt</hi> the upper End, were, both that herein they might differ from the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Ancient Heathen, who both wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped towards the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> god, the Heathen gods Ape, the Devil: And alſo for other ends, as becauſe our Saviour, in whoſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48970:60"/>name we Chriſtians worſhip the Father, is called the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and the whole work of our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Redemption was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and many ſuch Reaſons they had why they ſhould make the upper end of their Churches towards the <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then that the <hi>Eaſt</hi> was the upper end, Reaſon taught them to Place that which was moſt Sacred and worthy in the uppermoſt place, as we our ſelves uſe to do with perſons, and things which we account moſt excellent and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. So they did not adore to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Altar, becauſe it was ſet in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> but therefore they adored towards the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> becauſe the Altar was placed there, as in the higheſt and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt place. But in caſe ſome of the Churches were irregular, and ſtood not <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> yet they ſtill placed the Altar, in that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48970:61"/>place which was accounted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt, and thitherward did tender their Devotions, even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Altar, whereever pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And this is plain out of St. <hi>Chriſoſtom's</hi> and St. <hi>Baſill's</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies, yea, the Liturgies of all the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches and Fathers, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn Adoration towards the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar wherever placed.</p>
            <p>Obj.
<note place="margin">Conformiſts Looſe in their Lives.</note> 
               <hi>They that are ſo ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, are commonly men that have no-Religion in their Lives, but are all Outſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis no Argument, which is fetcht from the wickedneſs of the Perſon againſt the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Action; for by this way of Reaſoning, to Adminiſter the Holy Sacrament, to give Alms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be concluded evil Actions, becauſe wicked men oft do them. If the Action in it ſelf be not evil, 'tis no matter what the perſon is; indeed they that do a good Action ill,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48970:61"/>to them it becomes Sin; as to give Alms to be ſeen of Men: ſo to give God outward worſhip is good, but he that gives it Him without inward worſhip, and ſubmiſſion of his will to His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, he plays the Hipocrite, and ſo his worſhip becomes ſin to him. Our Saviour forbids not his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to do that Righteouſneſs which the Phariſees did, but to do more to exceed it; Nor did he forbid them to make clean the Outſide, buthe forbad them to content themſelves with that, and commands them to make the Inſide clean in the firſt place. Nor did he forbid men to do the leſs things of the Law, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to be more careful of the Greater; not only to Tithemint, but cheifly to Reſpect Righteouſneſs and Judgment. <hi>Theſe ye ought to have done, and not leave the other undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the Objection ſpoken in General, of all that outward
<pb facs="tcp:48970:62"/>
               <hi>Decorum</hi> in Gods worſhip, is a falſe Slaunder; for there are a great number of Holy and Pious men which ſerve God entirely both with outward and inward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and there are many noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Debauched livers that are not for outward worſhip. Our Saviour bids us Judge a Tree by the fruits; we can look no furth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the outſide; If I ſee a man worſhip God, with his body, devoutly and reverently, I ſhall rather think and believe he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips God with his Soul too, then he that pretends only to inward worſhip, and affords me no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mark or ſign of it. I ſhall rather judge that to be Gold which Gliſters, than that which doth not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48970:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
